Guide to the Charles James Hendley Papers TAM.109
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series II: Writings and Notes, 1914-1962
  - Subseries IIB: Notes, Drafts and Fragments, 1930-1962
    Subseries IIB contains a wide variety of notes, drafts and writing fragments. There are notebooks dating from 1928 through 1962 in which Hendley recorded everything from gardening tips and personal to-do lists to research on educational, labor and economics topics; outlines and draft portions of planned articles; meeting notes; lists of textbooks and citations; information gleaned from daily reading ofThe New York Times and other news sources (he also pasted in a number of clippings); and random jottings and ideas. Cards were used for many of his notes and also for names, addresses and information gleaned from canvassing he did in the Bronx on behalf of the American Labor Party.
    - Notebooks, 1938-1947 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Notebooks, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Notebooks, 1952-1953 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Notebooks, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Notebooks, 1956-1957 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Notebooks, 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Notebooks, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Notebooks: Economics, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Notebooks: Social Studies Miscellaneous Suggestions, [1928] (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Notes: Names and Addressses, undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Notes and Drafts: Academic Freedom, 1950, 1954, undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Notes and Drafts: The Catholic Hierarchy Challenges American Institutions, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Notes and Drafts: Economic, Social and Political Issues and Topics, [1933]-1956 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Notes and Drafts: Economic, Social and Political Issues and Topics, undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Notes and Drafts: Educational Issues, 1940s (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Notes and Drafts: Educational Issues, 1951-1960 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Notes and Drafts: Educational Issues, undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Notes and Drafts: History of Public Schools, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Notes and Drafts: Political Meetings, 1956-1960 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Notes and Drafts: Teachers Union - Conflict and Expulsion from AFT, 1940-1941, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Notes and Drafts: Teachers Union - Post-AFT, Pre-CIO, 1941-1943 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Notes and Drafts: Teachers Union - Salary Issues, 1930s (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Notes and Drafts: Teachers Union - Various Issues and Topics (I), 1930s (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Notes and Drafts: Teachers Union - Various Issues and Topics (II), 1930s (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Notes and Drafts: Teachers Union - Various Issues and Topics, 1940s (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Notes and Drafts: Teachers Union - Various Issues and Topics, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Notes and Drafts: The Daily Worker, 1952, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Notes (Cards): Citations and Call Slips, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Notes (Cards): Educational and Teachers Union Topics, 1942-1945, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Notes (Cards): Educational and Teachers Union Topics, 1946-1952 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Notes (Cards): Educational and Teachers Union Topics (I), undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Notes (Cards): Educational and Teachers Union Topics (II), undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Notes (Cards): Names, Addresses and Canvassing Notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Notes (Cards): Notes on Gus Hall Speech at National Communist Party Meeting, Mar 1950 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Notes (Cards): Transit Issues, 1948-1950, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Notes (Cards): Various Topics, 1942-1943, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Notes (Cards): Various Topics, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Notes (Cards): Various Topics, 1947-1951 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Notes (Cards): Various Topics, undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Notes (Cards): War Topics, 1942, undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
- Series III: Teachers Union of the City of New York Files, 1925-1962
  This series follows the history of the Union through its various affiliations. Each one of the first five subseries highlights activities, correspondence, financial and administrative material, communication with members, educational conferences, meeting minutes, publications and specific issues of importance associated with a particular period.
  The first subseries, focusing on its AFT affiliation as Local 5, contains a good deal of material concerning conflicts within the local, competing internal factions, the 1935 walkout and formation of the rival Teachers Guild, and final expulsion from the AFT. Attempts to rejoin the AFT are documented in the second subseries, while the third reflects the Union's affiliation with the CIO. The next two subseries document the Union's continued affiliation with the United Public Workers of America after the UPWA was expelled from the CIO and its final years as an independent union, touching on such topics as school integration and responses to anti-communist investigations. The last subseries highlights a number of special groups within the Union that were of particular interest to Charles Hendley - the Educational Policies Committee, the Teachers Union Institute and various political action committees. Also included is material reflecting the time Hendley spent, after his retirement from teaching, as an organizing field representative for the National Teachers Division of the UPWA/CIO.
  - Subseries IIIA: Teachers Union of NYC, American Federation of Teachers (AFT), Local 5, 1925-1941
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Due to the fragile nature of the originals, General Meeting Minutes and Membership Meeting Minutes in box 19 are accessible on microfilm only in the Tamiment reading room: Call Number R-7435 and R-7435A.
    - Activities (Overviews), undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Answer to Board of Examiners Recommendations Concerning Probationary Teachers, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Ching Chong and the School Commissioners, A Burlesque Operetta, Libretto by Mabel L. Rees and Collaborators (Presented by Local 5), 1931 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Clerks Interest Committee, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Communication with Members, 1930-1936 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Communication with Members, 1937-1939 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Communication with Members, 1940-1941 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Communication with Members, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Communication with Members (George Washington High School), 1927-1933 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Conflict: 1935 Crisis and Walkout, 1934-1935 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Conflict: 1935 Crisis and Walkout (Clippings) (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Conflict: 1935 Crisis and Walkout (Hearing Transcript), Jun 7, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Conflict: Expulsion from AFT, Aug 1940 - Nov 1940 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Conflict: Expulsion from AFT, Dec 1940 - Jan 1941 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Conflict: Expulsion from AFT, Feb 1941 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Conflict: Expulsion from AFT, Mar 1941 - Apr 1941 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Conflict: Expulsion from AFT, May 1941 - 1942 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Conflict: Expulsion from AFT, [1941] (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Conflict: Expulsion from AFT, undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Conflict: Expulsion from AFT (College Teachers Local 537), 1940-1941 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Conflict: Expulsion from AFT (George Hartman Attack on Union), 1939-1941 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Conflict: Expulsion from AFT (Notes, Drafts, Fragments), undated (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Conflict: Expulsion from AFT (Opposition Documents), 1940, undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Conflict: Factions, 1931-1936 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Conflict: Factions, 1937-1940, undated (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence, 1930-1938 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence, 1939-1941, undated (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Educational Conferences, 1937-1941 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Financial and Other Administrative Materials, 1928-1932 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Financial and Other Administrative Materials, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Financial and Other Administrative Materials, 1934-1935 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Financial and Other Administrative Materials, 1936-1939 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Financial and Other Administrative Materials, 1940-1941, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Harlem Committee, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Issues: Affiliation with American Labor Party, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Issues: Alertness Requirement, 1931 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Issues: Anti-War, 1939-1940, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Issues: City Budget - Retrenchment in Public Education, 1932-1941, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Issues: Overcrowded Classrooms, 1937-1940, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Issues: Penny Milk, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Issues: Residency Requirement Proposal (Ordinance #7), 1932 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Issues: Salaries, 1929-1932 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Issues: Salaries, 1933-1941, undated (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Issues: Salaries (Joseph McKee), 1933, undated (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Issues: Salaries (Mayor Walker 1932 Pay Cut) (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Issues: Salaries (Mayor Walker 1932 Pay Cut) - Clippings, May 1932 - Aug 1932 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Issues: State Aid to Education, 1938-1941 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Issues: Taxation, 1938-1940 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Legislative Program, 1934-1940, undated (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Membership Recruitment, 1925-1941, undated (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Minutes: Committee on Character Education, 1930 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Minutes: Delegate Assembly, 1933-1941 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Minutes: Executive Board, 1929-1939 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Minutes: Executive Board, 1940-1941 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Minutes: General Meetings, 1918-1929 (Box 19, Folder 1-14)
      Existence and Location of Copies
      Microfilm R-7435 and R-7435A
    - Minutes: Membership Meetings, 1930-1942 (Box 19, Folder 15-26)
    - Minutes: Trade Union Unity Conference, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Proposal for World's Fair Labor Exhibit, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Publications: College Teacher and the Trade Union, [1936] (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Publications: Handbook and Constitution, 1937, 1939 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Publications: New York Teacher, 1935, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - Publications: Protect Your Job and Promote Good Teaching, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - Publications: Statement of Local 5 on Proposed Revocation of Its Charter, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - Publications: Teachers and the Economic Situation, 1932 (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - Publications: The Union Teacher and Teacher News, 1927-1937 (Box 7, Folder 35)
    - Statements, Positions on Various Educational Issues, 1930-1940, undated (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - Teachers Union Auxiliary, 1930, undated (Box 7, Folder 37)
    - Teachers Union of NYC, Local 537 (New York College Teachers), 1936, 1939-1941, undated (Box 7, Folder 38)
    - Vocational School Issues, 1940, [1941] (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Subseries IIIB: Teachers Union of NYC, Unaffiliated (After Expulsion from AFT), 1941-1943
    - Attempts to Rejoin AFT, 1941-1942 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Communication with Members, 1941-1943, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1941 - Aug 1943 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Educational Conferences, 1942-1943 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Financial and Other Administrative Materials, 1941-1942 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Financial and Other Administrative Materials: Accountant Reports, 1942 - Aug 1943 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Financial and Other Administrative Materials: Union Elections, 1942-1943 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Harlem Committee: Harlem Teachers Can Handle War Time Delinquency, 1942 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Issues: Coudert Interim Report, Analysis by George Strayer, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Issues: Rising Costs and Excess Profits Tax, 1941 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Issues: School Budget (Teacher Dismissals), 1942-1943 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Issues: Wartime, 1941-1942 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Minutes: Executive Board, 1941-1943 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Minutes: Committee Chairmen, 1942-1943 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Teachers Union (New York College Teachers), 1942, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Teachers Union (Private School Section): Yeshiva News, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Subseries IIIC: Teachers Union of NYC, Congress of Industrial Organizatons (CIO), Local 555, 1943-1950
    - Affiliation with State, County and Municipal Workers of America (SCMWA), CIO, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Biennial State Convention: New York District SCMWA, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Brooklyn College and Harry Gideonse, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Communication with Members, 1943-1945 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Communication with Members, 1946-1950 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Communication with Members, undated (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Conference of Representatives of CIO Teachers Unions, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - CIO Recruitment, 1944-1950, undated (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Constitution and Revisions, 1941, 1943-1946 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Convention: New York District SCMWA, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Convention: New York District United Public Workers of America (UPWA), 1946 (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence, Sep 1943 - 1944 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence, 1945-1946 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence, 1947-1948, undated (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Educational Conferences, 1944, 1945, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - Educational Conferences: Education for One World (Publication of 9th Annual Educational Conference), 1945 (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - Election of 1944 (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - Financial and Other Administrative Materials, 1943-1944 (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - Financial and Other Administrative Materials, 1945-1946 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Financial and Other Administrative Materials, 1947-1950, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Financial and Other Administrative Materials: Accountant Reports, 1943-1945 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Financial and Other Administrative Materials: re The CIO News, 1943-1947, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Financial and Other Administrative Materials: George Washington High School, 1943-1946, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Financial and Other Administrative Materials: Union Elections, 1944-1950 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Greater New York CIO Council, 1944-1947, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Harlem Committee, 1943-1944 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Industrial Arts, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Issues: Ethel Kunis Case (Anti-Union Bias), 1946 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Issues: Inter-Cultural Education, undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Issues: Overcrowded Classrooms, 1941-1943, undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Issues: Post-War Jobs and Veterans, 1945, undated (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Issues: Salaries, 1944-1947 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Issues: Salaries, 1948-1949, undated (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Issues: School Budget, 1944-1948 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Issues: School Budget, 1949-1950, undated (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Issues: Substitutes, 1944-1948 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Issues: Teaching Load in Special Subjects, 1949 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Lederman, Abraham v. Board of Education of the City of New York (Draft of Proposed Complaint), 1949 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Legislative Program, 1943-1950, undated (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Legislative Program: Condon-Wadlin Bill/Teachers' Right to Strike, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Minutes: Executive Board, 1943-1947 (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Minutes: National Teachers Division Committee, 1945-1948, undated (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Minutes: New York State Executive Board, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - Minutes: Staff, [1944]-1946 (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - New York District Joint Board (includes Board Minutes), 1943-1944 (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - New York District Joint Board (includes Board Minutes), 1945, undated (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Pledges of Support to President Truman, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 29)
    - Publications: CIO - The CIO News, 1942, 1944, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 30)
    - Publications: CIO - Economic Outlook, 1945-1947 (Box 9, Folder 31)
    - Publications: CIO, Various, 1943-1948 (Box 9, Folder 32)
    - Publications: New Notes and College Administrative Staff News, 1945, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - Publications: New York Teacher News, 1946, 1947, 1949 (Box 9, Folder 34)
    - Publications: News of State County & Municipal Workers, Nov 23, 1944 (Box 9, Folder 35)
    - Publications: The Right to a Good Education, Jun 1944 (Box 9, Folder 36)
    - Publications: Schools and the Fight for Peace and Freedom, [1947] (Box 9, Folder 37)
    - Publications: Schools for Victory and Safeguard their Future, 1942, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 38)
    - Statements, Positions on Various Educational Issues, 1943-1950, undated (Box 9, Folder 39)
    - Support for Austin-Mahoney Fair Educational Practices Bill, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 40)
    - Vocational School Issues, 1942-1944, undated (Box 9, Folder 41)
  - Subseries IIID: Teachers Union of NYC, United Public Workers of America (UPWA), 1950-1952
    - Anti-CIO Pamphlet, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Communication with Members, 1952, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Issues: Puerto Rican Schoolchildren, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Issues: Salaries, 1950, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Issues: School Budget, 1950-1952 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Issues: Timone Resolution, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Publications: On the Record, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Publications: Teachers Bulletin, 1950-1951 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Publications: re Searchlight, An Expose of New York City Schools, 1951 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Subseries IIIE: Teachers Union of NYC, Independent, 1953-1962
    - Communication with Members, 1954-1962, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1952-1960 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Educational Conferences, 1953-1962 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Issues: School Budget, 1954-1955 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Issues: School Integration, 1953-1959 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Issues: Witch-Hunt (Anti-Communist), 1952-1955 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Parent-Teacher Forums, 1954-1956 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Publications: Teacher News, 1954-1961 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Publications: Teachers Bulletin, 1953-1954 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Statements, Positions on Various Educational Issues, 1953-1957 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Subseries IIIF: Teachers Union of NYC - Organizing, Educational Policy, Professional Development and Political Action Groups, 1936-1961
    - Educational Policies Committee, 1936, 1944-1953 (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Educational Policies Committee, 1954-1955 (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Educational Policies Committee, 1956-1961, undated (Box 10, Folder 22)
    - Educational Policies Committee: Meeting Minutes, 1956-1957 (Box 10, Folder 23)
    - Educational Policies Committee: Meeting Minutes, 1958-1961 (Box 10, Folder 24)
    - National Teachers Division (UPWA/CIO): Hendley as Field Representative, 1946-1948 (Box 10, Folder 25)
    - National Teachers Division (UPWA/CIO): Hendley as Field Representative - Activities in Buffalo, NY, 1945-1947, undated (Box 10, Folder 26)
    - National Teachers Division (UPWA/CIO): Hendley as Field Representative - Activities in Providence, RI, 1947 (Box 10, Folder 27)
    - National Teachers Division (UPWA/CIO): Hendley as Field Representative - Monthly Organizers Reports, 1948 (Box 10, Folder 28)
    - National Teachers Division (UPWA/CIO): Hendley as Field Representative - Personal Correspondence, 1946-1948 (Box 10, Folder 29)
    - Political Action Committees, 1944-1948, undated (Box 10, Folder 30)
    - Teachers Union Institute, Inc., 1941-1945 (Box 10, Folder 31)
    - Teachers Union Institute, Inc., 1946 (Box 10, Folder 32)
    - Teachers Union Institute, Inc., 1947-1949, undated (Box 10, Folder 33)
    - Teachers Union: Stationery and Forms - Various, 1943, undated (Box 10, Folder 34)
- Series IV: Academic Freedom Material, 1928-1961
  This series focuses on challenges to academic freedom from the late 1930s through the late 1950s, emphasizing the Rapp-Coudert Committee investigations and post-war red scare. The impact of these efforts, particularly the harassment and dismissal of many teachers, is documented through correspondence, court documents, articles, pamphlets, newspaper clippings, and other material, much of it generated by the Teachers Union of NYC. Charles Hendley's own appearance before Rapp-Coudert is documented. Also included are a number of articles and publications of those opposing the Union, such as The Educational Signpost and The Tablet.
  - Academic Freedom: General, 1928-1949 (Box 10, Folder 35)
  - Academic Freedom: General, 1950-1961, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Feinberg Law, 1949-1953, undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Foes: The Educational Signpost, 1938-1947 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Foes: Various Publications, 1938-1953 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Internal Security Committee of the U.S. Senate: Hendley Appearance, 1952 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - McNaboe Investigation and William Randolph Hearst, 1936 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Rapp-Coudert Committee (New York State Joint Legislative Committee on the State Education System), 1940 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Rapp-Coudert Committee, Jan 1941 - May 1941 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Rapp-Coudert Committee, Jun 1941 - Dec 1941 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Rapp-Coudert Committee, 1942-1943, 1951-1952, undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Rapp-Coudert Committee: Coudert and Boris Brasol, 1941-1942, undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Rapp-Coudert Committee: Hendley and the Teachers Union, 1940 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Rapp-Coudert Committee: Hendley and the Teachers Union, 1940-1942 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Teacher Harassment, Dismissals, 1933-1939 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Teacher Harassment, Dismissals, 1940-1949 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Teacher Harassment, Dismissals, 1950 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Teacher Harassment, Dismissals, 1951 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Teacher Harassment, Dismissals, Feb 1952 - Oct 1952 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Teacher Harassment, Dismissals, Nov 1952 - Dec 1952 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Teacher Harassment, Dismissals, 1953 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Teacher Harassment, Dismissals, 1954-1957 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Teacher Harassment, Dismissals, 1958-1959, undated (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - Teacher Harassment, Dismissals: Louis Jaffe, 1948 - [1952] (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Teacher Harassment, Dismissals: Sylvia Schneiderman, 1950 (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - Teacher Harassment, Dismissals: Dale Zysman, 1941-1942 (Box 11, Folder 25)
- Series V: Subject Files, 1914-1962
  This series contains a wide variety of materials touching on Hendley's professional, political and cultural interests. Examples include federal aid to education, the Spanish Civil War, anti-communism and red-baiting, civil rights and the segregation of schools, separation of church and state, reading retardation and education during wartime. Hendley's involvement in Socialism and in the Communist Party is reflected, including his association with The Worker. Organizations such as the American Federation of Teachers (AFT), the American Labor Party (ALP) and the National Education Association (NEA) are represented, along with smaller teacher associations and teacher unions outside the New York area. Files are included on individuals such as Elizabeth Gurley Flynn, Morris Schappes and the Rosenbergs. There are many newpaper clippings, collected over thirty years, that document educational, political and labor issues. The series contains examples of many serials as well as pamphlets and other publications, including several of particular interest -- The Flivver King by Upton Sinclair, On Scabs by Jack London, a small book of anti-Nazi humor, and The Challenger, a comic with liberal superheroes published by the Interfaith Committee of the Protestant Digest in the mid-1940s.